A Guide to the Emmanuel Episcopal Church (Virginia Beach, Va.), Records, 1723-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Emmanuel Episcopal Church (Virginia Beach, Va.), Records, 1723-1999
The Library of Virginia
42001
3 reels
Emmanuel Episcopal Church (Virginia Beach, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for microfilming by Emmanuel Episcopal Church, 25 June 2005.
Biographical Information
Emmanuel Episcopal Church was built in 1843 in the Kempsville, Princess Anne County (now Virginia Beach). David Walke donated the land on which the church was built. It was the first church to be built in Lynnhaven Parish under the Protestant Episcopal Church. The original church was destroyed by fire in 1943. The present church building was consecrated in 1947.
Scope and Content
Records, 1723-1999, of Emmanuel Episcopal Church in Virginia Beach, including vestry books (20 November 1723-8 December 1959), registers and parish registers (1838-1999), registers of church services (1 March 1967-31 December 1998), financial register (1923-1929), and loose papers such as anniversary booklets, correspondence, deeds, histories, and miscellaneous burials, confirmations, and vestry minutes.
The registers and parish registers, 1838-1999, include includes lists of baptisms, burials, confirmations, communicants, histories, marriages, and rectors. The Parish registers include indexes. The registers of church services include the following information: date/day of service, type of service, place of service, hour of service, number in attendance, communions, officiant/preacher, and memoranda.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Vestry Books, 20 November 1723-8 December 1959; II. Registers and Parish Registers, 1838-1999; III. Registers of Church Services, 1 March 1967-31 December 1998; IV. Financial Register, 1923-1929; V. Loose Papers.
MISC. REEL 4838 contains in this order: Vestry Book, 20 November 1723-16 November 1892; Vestry Book, 28 November 1892-14 August 1947; Vestry Book, 6 March 1951-8 December 1959. MISC. REEL 4839 contains in this order: Register, 1838-1913; Register, 1900-1948; Register, 1929-1936; Register, 1947-1973; Register, 1964-1976; Parish Register, 1973-1976; Parish Register, 1976-1978; Parish Register, 1978-1981; Parish Register, 1981-1983; Parish Register, 1983-1985; Parish Register, 1985-1999. MISC. REEL 4840 contains in this order: Register of Church Services, 1 March 1967-29 May 1977; Register of Church Services, 10 November 1991-31 December 1998; Register of Church Services, 1 June 1977-11 December 1985; Register of Church Services, 15 December 1985-10 November 1991; Financial Register, 1923-1929; Loose Papers.
Contents List
- Vestry Books, 20 November 1723-8 December 1959 (Reel 4838)
  - Vestry Book, 20 November 1723-16 November 1892, This volume is a photocopy of negative photostats. (Reel 4838)
  - Vestry Book, 28 November 1892-14 August 1947 (Reel 4838)
  - Vestry Book, 6 March 1951-8 December 1959 (Reel 4838)
- Registers and Parish Registers, 1838-1999 (Reel 4839)
  - Register, 1838-1913, This volume is a photocopy of negative photostats. (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1838-1911; confirmations, 1838-1911; communicants, 1838-1884; marriages, 1839-1913; burials, 1838-1911; and communicants, 1888-1891.
  - Register, 1900-1948 (Reel 4839)
    Includes history, 1900, 1923, 1926, 1927; baptisms, 1901-1905, 1923-1947 (p. 34-43); confirmations, 1923-1943 (p. 76-80); communicants, 1925 (p. 88-94); marriages, 1923-1929, 1948 (p. 112-113); and burials, 1923-1928, 1947 (p. 128-129).
  - Register, 1929-1936 (Reel 4839)
    Includes rectors (Rev. Pearson Hill Sloan, 5 June 1929); historical data (p. 43); communicants, 1929-1935 (p. 46-50, 58-63); baptisms, 1929-1936 (p. 70-77); confirmations, 1929-1935 (p. 114-119); burials, 1930-1936 (p. 134-135); and marriages, 1930-1936 (p. 154-168).
  - Register, 1947-1973, This volume is incomplete and water-damaged. (Reel 4839)
    Includes rectors, 1947-1973 (p. 45); communicants, 1948-1970 (p. 50-71); baptisms, 1947-1973 (p. 72-109); confirmations, 1948-1969 (p. 114-129); burials, 1950-1973 (p. 132-135); marriages, 1949-1973 (p. 150-177).
  - Register, 1964-1976 (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1969-1973 (p. 94-99); confirmations, 1969-1976 (p. 138-146); communicants, 1964-1973 (p. 158-187).
  - Parish Register, 1973-1976 (Reel 4839)
    Includes rectors, 1842-1973; historical data "All records prior to 1943 burned in fire of that year"; baptisms, 1974-1976; baptized persons, 1963-1976; communicants, 1973-1976; marriages, 1974-1976; and burials, 1974-1975. Includes index.
  - Parish Register, 1976-1978 (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1976-1978; baptized persons, 1976-1978; confirmations, 1977-1978; communicants, 1976-1978; marriages, 1976-1978; and burials, 1977-1978. Includes index.
  - Parish Register, 1978-1981 (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1978-1981; baptized persons, 1979-1981; confirmations, 1979-1980; communicants, 1978-1981; marriages, 1979-1981; and burials, 1979-1981. Includes index.
  - Parish Register, 1981-1983 (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1981-1983; baptized persons, 1981-1983; confirmations, 1981-1982; communicants, 1981-1982; marriages, 1981-1983; and burials, 1981-1982. Includes index.
  - Parish Register, 1983-1985 (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1983-1985; baptized persons, 1983-1985; confirmations, 1983-1984; communicants, 1983-1984; marriages, 1983-1985; and burials, 1983-1985. Includes index.
  - Parish Register, 1985-1999 (Reel 4839)
    Includes baptisms, 1985-1990; baptized persons, 1985-2001; confirmations, 1985-1987; communicants, 1985-1988; marriages, 1985-1990; and burials, 1985-1999. Includes index.
- Registers of Church Services, 1 March 1967-31 December 1998 (Reel 4840)
  The registers of church services include the following information: date/day of service, type of service, place of service, hour of service, number in attendance, communions, officiant/preacher, and memoranda. These volumes were filmed out of chronological order. Register of Church Services, 10 November 1991-31 December 1998 was filmed after Register of Church Services, 1 March 1967-29 May 1977 and before Register of Church Services, 1 June 1977-11 December 1985.
  - Register of Church Services, 1 March 1967-29 May 1977 (Reel 4840)
  - Register of Church Services, 1 June 1977-11 December 1985 (Reel 4840)
  - Register of Church Services, 15 December 1985-10 November 1991 (Reel 4840)
  - Register of Church Services, 10 November 1991-31 December 1998 (Reel 4840)
    This volume was filmed out of chronological order. It was filmed after Register of Church Services, 1 March 1967-29 May 1977 and before Register of Church Services, 1 June 1977-11 December 1985.
- Financial Register, 1923-1929 (Reel 4840)
  Includes receipts and disbursements, 1923-1929 (p. 2-143); Norfolk Southern Railroad, 1923 (p. 145); contingent fund, 1923-1928 (p. 146-151).
- Loose Papers (Reel 4840)
  - Affidavits re. Emmanuel Episcopal Church Property (Reel 4840)
  - American Church Building Fund Commission (Reel 4840)
  - Anniversary Booklets (Reel 4840)
  - Burial Records (Reel 4840)
  - Confirmations (Reel 4840)
  - Correspondence (Reel 4840)
  - Deeds (Reel 4840)
  - Diocesan Census of Parishes (1852) (Reel 4840)
  - Emmanuel Church: A History for Parishioners / by Sandra A. Everton (Reel 4840)
  - Financial Records (Reel 4840)
  - Histories (Reel 4840)
  - Journal of the Fifty-Seventh Annual Convention of the Protestant Episcopal Church in Virginia (1852) (Reel 4840)
  - Letters of Transfer (Reel 4840)
  - Old Donation Church (Reel 4840)
  - Rectors at Emmanuel Episcopal Church (Reel 4840)
  - Valuable Items Inventory (Reel 4840)
  - Vestry Minutes, 12 October 1943-17 December 1944 (Reel 4840)